Welcome to preventing workplace gossip and other disruptive behavior.
My name is Lisa Smith, and I will be your trainer
today.
This course has two sections of information in section one,
we will discuss confidentiality in the workplace gossip, rumors and
personal information.
So let's start out by asking the question, what is
gossip Well, some people think that gossiping is like secret
telling, you know, sometimes it's considered to be fun and
interesting, and some people get a real ego boost by
being included in a chain of gossip.
Some people like being the topic of gossip.
Again, another ego boost that gossip can be very, very
hurtful.
Gossip can include things like rumors or unconfirmed reports attacks
on someone's personality and character, negative belittling or humiliating.
Talk about a peer intended to undermine them.
And gossip can also be factual, shared information that could
be confidential.
There is a term that's often used in pop culture
today called hot Goss.
This is a popular term and is sometimes viewed as
a social commodity.
You know, the person with the hottest Goss wins, but
ask yourself in your experience, does anyone really win When
gossip becomes the order of the day, sometimes gossip is
intentionally meant to harm someone, but on the other hand,
some people don't even realize they're gossiping.
They think they're just having a casual conversation about another
person about something that is none of their business.
Gossip can even be positive information that's being relayed, but
it's still gossip.
And quite often even positive information in a gossip session
turns into something negative.
So ask yourself, have you ever been the target of
workplace gossip And if so, how did it make you
feel This is a great place to stop the video.
And if you're in a group discuss amongst yourselves, what
that felt like if you're comfortable even take a minute
to relay your experience, share with the crowd, because this
is information that we really want to dive into, and
we don't want to make light of, if you're viewing
this alone, you can still stop the video for a
minute and just think about it.
And then when you're ready, click it back and move
forward.
How rumors get started.
Well, my dad used to always have the saying that's
how rumors get started when you would misunderstand something that
was said about someone or even maybe about yourself.
So how to misunderstandings actually happen Well, they can happen
a lot of different ways.
And one, one small misunderstanding can turn into fodder for
rumors, which can devolve into a wildfire of gossip.
The best way to limit the damage of a wildfire
is to make sure the environment is not wildfire friendly.
So clear communication is a necessity for creating a fire
retardant working environment.
So ask yourself, how do misunderstandings happen Have you ever
been the victim or the target or the unknowing participants
of the misunderstanding I know that you've all heard of
the game telephone, right And so this is a game
that is often played with kids to help them understand
how a rumor can get started or how you can
hear one thing and repeat it so many times that
by the time it gets down the line, the entire
original message has been distorted into something that doesn't even
look like what the original message was.
So this is an exercise that again, if you're in
a group setting, it would be great time to stop
the video and go through the exercise.
So at the beginning of the game, the first person
is going to whisper a sentence into the next person's
ear.
You can decide whatever that is.
It can be pre-planned by your facilitator, or, you know,
you can just make something up during the game.
Each player will whisper the sentence into the next person's
ear until it reaches the last player in line.
At the end of the game, the last player says
the sentence out loud so that everyone can hear how
much it has changed from the first whisper at the
beginning of the circle or the line rules for the
telephone game, the word or phrase can only be whispered
once.
So players must pay close attention.
The word or phrase should never be too familiar.
You want to make sure it changes as it's whispered.
So if you say something like it is what it
is.
Everyone's heard that 10,000 times, and that's going to be
pretty clear that if you say something that is different
and is not a catch or not something usual, then
it has a better chance of actually simulating the transfer
of gossip.
And then finally, only one player.
The first player should know what the word or phrase
is.
The facilitator of the game may wish to have the
original phrase or word written down so that at the
very end we can corroborate what it actually was with
what that final player believes he or she heard.
Okay.
So click, pause, and get started.
I hope you enjoyed the telephone game.
And if you are viewing this alone, play it at
home with some family members or friends, and it's a,
it can be a really good time and also a
great teaching tool for yourself and for your family members,
understanding the red flags of workplace gossip versus harmless venting.
You know, sometimes we just need to vent and sometimes
we're venting about someone else.
And sometimes that's okay because we don't need to bottle
things up and suppress them to the point to where
we're anxious and depressed.
And we dread coming to work every day.
No, of course not.
But there is a time and a place and an
appropriate chain of command for expressing your events.
So keep that in mind, John, the head manager of
Acme was giving a presentation about a new product launching
next week.
During this meeting, Mandy kept interrupting the meeting, complaining about
how he's not giving them enough time to prepare to
launch and how it's going to fail.
John had to ask Mandy three times to stop interrupting.
Now let's look at what a red flag might look
like.
John starts talking about Mandy.
When she leaves the meeting stating how rudely she behaved.
John then starts complaining about what has happened at past
meetings and company get togethers.
That would be a red flag for gossip, as opposed
to harmless venting, which might be when Mandy leaves the
office.
John states, that he cannot believe she interrupted him three
times.
He doesn't make any accusations about Mandy's intent for interrupting.
And he leaves it at that.
That would be harmless venting, but how would we respond
to John in either scenario But especially in the red
flag scenario, we might say something like John, I share
your concern about Mandy's interruptions that telling me isn't going
to make it better.
I think you need to talk to Mandy.
I'm happy to help you think through how you could
approach that conversation.
Remember everyone, Vince, we're all human and we get under
each other's skin.
Yes, but there is a fine line between venting and
gossiping.
Once you stop stating facts and start making accusations and
assumptions that we're venting can turn into gossiping.
Unnecessary gossip creates many negative consequences and it can create
a lot of commotion in the workplace.
Some of the negative effects of gossip might be, of
course, like I said before, it spreads like wildfire, right
Rumors will circulate.
And the truth becomes virtually unrecognizable.
This negative effect of gossip could be that it results
in a loss of productivity causes coworkers to choose upsides
definitely will lower morale people lose trust in each other
and turnover and hostile work environment issues become much more
prevalent not to mention the fact that gossip is really
a major drain on time and money.
The actual cost of the weekly time spent gossiping in
an average workplace can be very high.
This wasted time is found on a consistent basis and
comes in many forms.
This drain on time and money could be in person
at the office coffee machine or in whispers over a
desk.
When we should be working, it can be via direct
messenger online again, when we should be working through email,
when we should be working, you may use an app
like WhatsApp, for instance, and you may have colleague groups,
which can be very productive, but if not used properly
and if used for gossip, WhatsApp, or signal or any
of those other apps, including text messaging can be very
destructive and text messaging while actually in the same room
at the same meeting can be not only very disrespectful,
but also very destructive.
And it's, it tends to single the two or three
people out who were in that text message group as
being as against the rest of the crowd can be
very divisive.
And instead of learning something we should be taking seriously
at that team meeting, we're just in our own little
world, gossiping negative effects can also be very detrimental to
the victim of gossip.
People who we gossip about.
In-depth oftentimes with a hurt reputation, maybe things have been
said that are untrue.
They sound juicy.
And boy, are we ready to open our ears and
listen, but is it true And if it is true,
does it matter The victim of gossip may already be
feeling terrible because if what you are saying is true,
it could be very unflattering information and that person may
not be happy to think about it.
And it may be something they're struggling with.
So knowing that other folks are gossiping around the office
will continue to lower their self-esteem could possibly plunge them
into a depression and increase anxiety.
Sadly enough suicides have been committed over workplace gossip.
Sometimes the workplace becomes like a playground at school and
we know how brutal children can be with each other.
They don't have the maturity oftentimes to make the decision
that something is healthy or not healthy or acceptable or
unacceptable in a social circle, sadly enough, sometimes adults don't
have that ability, or I don't know, they just don't
take the initiative to exercise the ability to make those
same decisions and suicidal thoughts and actions may result.
Gossip is ultimately divisive gossip, divides and conquers a workplace
and not in a good way.
We must take the power that gossip carries very seriously.
The subject or the target of the gossip is an
actual victim and harassment cases have shown this.
This is not just the funny person that we're talking
about or the person everybody thinks is ridiculous.
Or did you hear what Sally did Saturday night Now
this can actually turn into a harassment case and it
is very serious participants eventually choose upsides.
And the workplace becomes a battlefield gossip gone, wild can
become slander, which may be illegal.
So what are some situations that trigger gossip Why do
we gossip Well, sometimes we gossip because it's the fear
of the unknown.
You know, humans are anxious people and you know, when
people feel like they are being kept in the dark,
this anxiety can manifest as gossip.
Sometimes people gossip because they crave a sense of belonging.
If someone believes they don't have information that the rest
of the team has, they will feel excluded and not
part of the team.
And so they may gossip to become a part of
a group that they feel left out of.
Sometimes people gossip, just because they need to feel superior,
they are envious, jealous, or they're just attention seeking people.
If someone feels insecure, they'll often try to tear others
down in the hope of making themselves feel better.
Most gossipers honestly are pure attention seekers.
Now I know we've all been gossipers.
We've all done it.
Nobody's without gossip, guilt.
And where are we A pure attention seeker in that
moment where we jealous, where we envious, where we needing
to feel superior I don't know.
I think that's a personal question.
We all have to ask ourselves, but at the end
of the day, if you are gossiping, your intentions were
not pure.
You know, because seeking to reach out and create a
chain of help for someone in need is not gossip.
So remember the difference, person may begin gossiping because they're
angry.
They may want to take revenge on someone who made
them angry, who made them feel hurt.
So one hot Goss can spawn another hot Goss.
And before you know it, we're back to the battlefield
and we're all angry.
And then for some people, gossip is just a way
of passing time.
You know, I had a friend who we called the
mouth of the south and she was just bored a
lot.
And her gossiping tendencies were usually the highest when she
didn't have a lot of work to do at home
or at the workplace.
So employees must take accountability for their own free time
and use it wisely.
If we finish up an assignment quicker than we expected,
or maybe we're having a slow day in the workplace,
not many customers are coming through.
Seems like there's not a lot to do.
And we're a little bored.
Well, let's grab a broom or, you know, reorganize a
desk or something to avoid ourselves from falling into a
big gossip party, just because we're bored.
Let's look at a case study.
Sally has missed a week of work unexpectedly.
She has been an employee of Acme for 10 years
and rarely misses work.
This has been hard for the team because Sally not
there to support them through a huge inspection that they
have been anticipating for months.
Here are some examples of the gossip that could spread
about Sally missing work.
Sally has COVID because I heard her sneeze the last
day she was here.
Sally was pulled into the office.
I bet she got fired.
I heard Sally on the phone with her husband talking
about planning a trip to the beach.
I bet she missed work to avoid the inspection.
Sally said her grandma was sick.
I think she died.
Is all of this gossip negative Well, maybe not.
I mean, Sally, having a grandmother who was sick and
dying, that's not negative.
It may not be true that it's not harmful to
Sally.
If that's the end of it, Sally has COVID.
That can be harmful.
It can also be a caring comment.
I'm worried about her.
I hope she doesn't have COVID but still at the
end of the day, we don't know what's happened with
Sally and it's gossip.
Certainly something like Sally getting fired or conspiring to avoid
the inspection that has been on everybody's minds for months.
That's certainly going to be harmful negative gossip.
Why don't we just stay away from the conversation altogether,
changing the subject and keeping it positive is one really
great way to combat gossip in the workplace.
So why don't we just redirect the conversation When you
hear gossip starting up, take control of the conversation at
the onset of the gossip center, your conversations on positive
topics, change the subject to work topics that don't include.
Other people take a personal interest in the other person.
People love to talk about themselves.
For example, ask what the person's plans are for the
weekend or what they're having for dinner.
People are less likely to want to gossip with you
if you're not engaging in the gossip.
So don't contribute any negative stories and don't respond to
anyone.
Else's hints that they have gossip to share.
Know when to walk away.
Some people will not get the hint by swiftly changing
the subject.
You may just need to kindly excuse yourself from the
conversation and let the person know that you don't want
to engage in the subject, or you could encourage positive
gossip.
You can easily spoil someone's attempt to gossip in a
negative fashion.
I simply paying a compliment to the person they're trying
to gossip about.
Here's a case study.
Meredith was having a snack, the break room with Bailey.
Alex walks in to get coffee ranting about how Christina
is so bossy and has no respect for her coworkers.
She steals credit for my ideas and always steps in
front of me for the prime projects.
He complains Meredith tries to talk him down.
She says, yes, Christina is bossy, but she's very talented.
Bailey interrupts and says, Hey, Alex, I really liked the
way you handled that Jones case.
Last week, Mr.
Jones can be Taft, but you really took care of
his concerns, Alex smirks and says, yeah, thanks.
He was tough.
Aly interrupts and says, yes, but you were tougher.
Alex says, I guess, and leaves the break room.
If you're working in a group, this would be a
great time to stop the video and evaluate both Meredith
and Bailey who did the best job and why, if
you're working alone, you can still stop the video and
think it through confidentiality, everything is not everyone's business.
So even when you're talking about yourself, believe it or
not people gossip about themselves.
Yeah.
It's true.
Have you ever heard of TMI too much information So
avoid oversharing your personal details, because maybe you want people
to talk about you.
Maybe that is your version of attention seeking.
Have you ever known someone like that who will talk
about themselves and basically hope you spread the message, things
like personal finances, of course, negative feelings about coworkers that
you have, religion, politics, health issues, dating, or your love
life in general activities that you do outside of work.
Some of these things in, in moderation are, are fine,
but oversharing is when it really becomes a burden on
the other individual.
And maybe the other individual's burden is they just don't
care.
They don't want to hear TMI, stop talking about yourself
all the time, or maybe it's a burden for them
to hold back from then repeating what you've told them.
Either way.
Don't give people more than they can bear, right Sharing
too much private information about your life feelings about your
coworkers and other sensitive subjects can be a breeding ground
for gossip to occur about you.
So to share or not to share, ask yourself a
few questions.
What is my intention with sharing this information Can the
information someone, or can it hurt me And how would
I feel if this information were to be spread around
the office And you might also add on how would
I feel when it's known I was the source of
this information.
When a conversation is none of your business closed door
meetings should be your first clue.
When people go behind a closed door, that is usually
a signal to the world that this is a private
conversation that's happening.
So if you're behind the door in the middle of
the conversation, understand that this is a private discussion.
And if you are on the other side of the
door, looking in, or trying to listen in, understand that
the closed door should be your first clue, that this
is none of your business, the door's closed because people
want privacy.
Therefore speculating on the conversation behind the door can only
lead to gossip and misinformation pressuring.
One of the participants to spill the tea is also
inappropriate conversations between HR and an employee management and an
employee or HR and management should remain confidential and are
not the business of anyone who is not in the
room.
When the conversation took place, let's look at a case
steady Pat's supervisor, Kay has called a meeting to discuss
the fact that a coworker has been diagnosed with COVID-19.
And pat was one of the people in the building
who has been exposed pat and K chat for a
few minutes.
And then pat clocks out and prepares to go home
while gathering her things.
Pat, who is visibly shaken is approached by Monroe, who
asks, why she's leaving so early in the day, what
happened in there Did you get fired Monroe asked pressuring
pat for answers, pat breaks and begins to cry saying
she's probably got COVID and she leaves in a hurry.
Monroe is now armed with a big decision, be the
hot Goss king, and try to find out if anyone
else has COVID or say nothing, realizing he does not
have all the facts has clearly overstepped with pat and
should now show compassion.
This is gut check time.
What would you do if you were in Monroe's position,
stop the video and discuss, or think it through on
your own hopping off of the gossip bandwagon.
It's pretty easy to hop on the bandwagon when gossip
is around that hopping off is a different story.
Once we've already become involved.
So think before you speak, put yourself in the other
person's shoes, don't say anything that you would not want
anyone saying about you and avoid putting yourself in the
position to gossip in the first place.
If you find that that's where you've landed, steer conversations
away from gossip and move them back to more productive
discussions, like something on a project that not the gossip
hop off.
The bandwagon questions to ask yourself to avoid boss up
are, is what I'm about to say.
True.
Is it harmless Is it necessary How would I feel
if someone said something similar about me, how would I
feel if I saw my words quoted in the daily
paper tomorrow How am I going to feel later if
I say this, or maybe even listen to this, does
gossiping honor my own personal values.
As the conversation take pleasure in the misfortune of others,
does this conversation have a negative emotional charge or seem
to perpetuate conflict or negativity Is this conversation hurt or
damage the reputation of others What I say these things
to the person's face.
And should I be saying these things to the person
instead of behind their back, it's always a good idea
to step back and ask yourself these questions.
When you're tempted to participate in rumors or gossip, and
remember simply hanging out and listening to gossip makes you
a part of the conversation, whether or not you ever
open your mouth guilty by association.
Some might say that in order to truly avoid gossip,
we must truly avoid gossip, section two management, confidentiality, what
to share and what not to share with your employees
closed door conversations with HR can be very intriguing to
the people on the other side of the door.
So remember this, unless otherwise stated all conversations with HR
are considered to be confidential and are not to be
shared with anyone.
Management must accept the fact that they do not have
a need to know regarding all conversations about employees and
their department.
Some conversations between employees and HR will not be shared
with managers and supervisors, managers, and supervisors don't like this
because they feel like they have a need to know.
This is not always the case.
Some confidential employee information comes in the version of, you
know, paperwork.
So maybe social security numbers, date of birth, marital status,
mailing address.
Those may be some things that are confidential.
Job application data like resume background checks and interview notes
may also find themselves in a confidential file, depending upon
what is written nines and tax forms, workers' comp and
FMLA claims any sort of employee medical information, including a
positive COVID test are all considered confidential and job termination
data.
The employee's resignation letter, termination records and unemployment insurance claims.
This is all confidential.
HR information managers and supervisors must maintain confidentiality in many
areas as well.
Discussions about employee relations issues, disciplinary actions, impending, layoffs, or
reductions in force terminations.
These are all very highly confidential workplace investigations over employee
misconduct.
Again, highly confidential, not to be shared, definitely the makings
of some good hot GOs that confidential do not share
ADA or EEOC issues, FMLA or other leave requests, employee
illnesses, even the most simple or obvious conditions like a
pregnancy for instance, should not be discussed in the workplace
between managers, supervisors, and staff.
Corporate email can be dangerous and feeding gossip.
So be careful information via email can be easily forward
to unauthorized eyes.
So when you have something that is confidential, be careful
what you say in email and who you say it
to.
So how would we address employee questions about confidential information
This comes up a lot in our managers and supervisors,
along with HR, all battle.
These questions that come from sources who don't have a
need to know managers must strive to answer questions with
the utmost professionalism.
Sometimes a more serious approach is needed.
When questions are asked that are obviously intended for the
gossip mill or some sort of personal agenda.
Even when a question is asked with the best of
intentions, some things are just not the business of others.
And as managers, there could be legal consequences for overstepping
boundaries.
For example, when someone asks, which coworker exposed me to
COVID, you might say something like, I cannot disclose that
information.
I'm sure if the person wants you to know, they
will tell you now, does that sound a little flippant
Maybe depending upon the tone you use, but you can
say it kindly, but it is very clear.
It lets them know that you're not going to disclose
this information.
Why is Sally out for a week Is she sick
Did she get fired Well, I'm sure if Sally wants
you to know, then she'll tell you, you know, something
along those lines, you don't want to say, well, she's
not sick and she didn't get fired.
Well, what is it Then You know, don't let them
lead you down the path of 20 questions.
I'm sure if Sally wants you to know, then she'll
tell you, Fred told me that John got into trouble
yesterday.
What did he do I'm not sure what you hope
to gain by asking this question.
You should not encourage Fred or anyone else to spread
gossip.
That's a very direct way to answer that question, but
you can also say it kindly, but it is professional.
Is it true that Billy got the black eye from
her spouse I'm not sure what relevance this topic has
to your position with our company.
Is there anything else I can assist you with Sometimes
you just have to face the most brutal questions that
are obviously meant for gossip with a very stern answer.
This might be a good time to stop the video
in a group setting and discuss some of the questions
that have come up in your departments and how you've
handled them and maybe how you can handle them differently.
Next time gossip and section seven of the N L
R a.
What is the NLRA Well, it stands for national labor
relations act.
Employers are encouraged to have no gossip policies.
Legal counsel should be consulted to be sure that the
language does not violate the NLRA 'cause section seven of
the NLRA says employees shall have the right to self-organize
to form join or assist labor organizations to bargain collectively
through representatives of their own choosing and to engage in
other concerted activities for the purpose of collective bargaining or
other mutual aid or protection.
So section seven basically provides that employees have the right
to engage in concerted activities for the purpose of mutual
aid or protection section seven rights belong to non-supervisory employees
in all types of workplaces, including those that do not
have unions.
Section seven does not however, apply to governmental employees at
the federal or state levels.
So here we're talking about private sector under the NLRA.
Your no gossip policy will be unlawful or illegal.
If it directly restricts employees from exercising, their section seven
rights or employees would reasonably construe the language in the
policy to prohibit section seven protected activity, or the policy
was implemented in response to union activity, or the policy
has been applied to restrict section seven activity.
In recent years, the NLRA ordered employers to resend no
gossip policies on the basis that the policies could be
construed to prohibit employees from discussing the terms and conditions
of their employment with other employees.
The bottom line non-supervisory employees cannot be barred from discussing
or complaining about working conditions, safety, wages, management, or unlawful
conduct, best practices for creating compliant.
No gossip policies might be to determine whether to take
action steps, to try and limit gossip in the workplace,
develop a policy that your organization is comfortable with in
terms of the parameters established by the NLRB decisions and
other applicable laws.
Now, remember I mentioned the national labor relations act, which
is then governed by the national labor relations board, which
is the NLRB implement the policy throughout employee discussions and
training on acceptable versus unacceptable behavior.
Take adverse action against employees only after a thorough investigation,
take adverse action against employees only after giving them the
right to explain their behavior and take adverse action against
employees under the policy.
Only after considering recent NLRB decisions, setting parameters to apply
to no gossip policies, make the subject of respect in
the workplace, a source of discussion on a regular basis.
And remember always consult legal counsel before implementing a no
gossip policy.
Every manager has responsibility in the workplace to make employees
feel safe.
Gossip can be a very threatening tool, used to make
coworkers feel unsafe in the workplace.
So what's a manager to do well.
Address the gossipers.
Don't be a part of the gossip address them, make
sure this is done in confidence.
So others cannot hear what is being discussed.
Talk to the person and try to understand what is
motivating them to spread boss it about another employee.
In some cases, there might be an underlying issue that
needs to be addressed.
Your end goal should be to help the person understand
the impact of their behavior and the consequences of what
will happen.
If it continues, take necessary action.
If a discussion with the gossiper has not put an
in to the behavior, then it's time to take action.
Managers should start with a verbal warning.
Then a formal written warning for the employee's file.
If HR has not created a policy about gossip, they
should be encouraged to do so.
Finally be the example don't get caught up in the
rumor mill employees will try to feed you gossip about
others for their own benefit.
Your job is to stop the gossip in its tracks.
One toxic person can drive your good employees away, especially
if they see that their behavior is going an addressed.
So if you want to keep your good faithful, loyal,
solid employees handle the gossip, stop it before it takes
root